<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="/forest/default.xsl"?>
<fr:tree xmlns:fr="http://www.forester-notes.org" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xmlns:xml="http://www.w3.org/XML/1998/namespace" root="false" base-url="/forest/">
  <fr:frontmatter>
    <fr:authors>
      <fr:author>
        <fr:link href="/forest/ahfrom/" title="Asta Halkjær From" uri="https://astahfrom.github.io/forest/ahfrom/" display-uri="ahfrom" type="local">Asta Halkjær From</fr:link>
      </fr:author>
    </fr:authors>
    <fr:date>
      <fr:year>2025</fr:year>
      <fr:month>8</fr:month>
      <fr:day>6</fr:day>
    </fr:date>
    <fr:uri>https://astahfrom.github.io/forest/software/</fr:uri>
    <fr:display-uri>software</fr:display-uri>
    <fr:route>/forest/software/</fr:route>
    <fr:title text="Software I Enjoy">Software I Enjoy</fr:title>
    <fr:taxon>Post</fr:taxon>
  </fr:frontmatter>
  <fr:mainmatter>
    <html:p>This page highlights some of the software that makes me happy.</html:p>
    <fr:tree show-metadata="false">
      <fr:frontmatter>
        <fr:authors>
          <fr:author>
            <fr:link href="/forest/ahfrom/" title="Asta Halkjær From" uri="https://astahfrom.github.io/forest/ahfrom/" display-uri="ahfrom" type="local">Asta Halkjær From</fr:link>
          </fr:author>
        </fr:authors>
        <fr:date>
          <fr:year>2025</fr:year>
          <fr:month>8</fr:month>
          <fr:day>6</fr:day>
        </fr:date>
        <fr:uri>https://astahfrom.github.io/forest/paperwm/</fr:uri>
        <fr:display-uri>paperwm</fr:display-uri>
        <fr:route>/forest/paperwm/</fr:route>
        <fr:title text="PaperWM">PaperWM</fr:title>
        <fr:taxon>Software</fr:taxon>
      </fr:frontmatter>
      <fr:mainmatter>
        <html:figure><html:img src="/forest/bafkrmihbdb7onay3aj7exay3rpi6puz46briolk5myhbauiuzq4vbaoen4.png" alt="Three windows: a terminal emulator with Neovim and two Firefox windows. The third Firefox window is only partially visible, indicating that it exists mostly off screen." />
  <html:figcaption>An infinite tape of windows.</html:figcaption></html:figure>
        <html:p><fr:link href="https://github.com/paperwm/PaperWM" type="external">PaperWM</fr:link> is a Gnome Shell extension that implements a <html:em>scrollable</html:em> tiling window manager. Imagine something like i3/Sway but instead of tiling your windows inside a rectangle, it lays them out on an infinite tape extending to the right. I only ever used used xmonad for a little bit a long time ago, so I am not going to compare PaperWM to tiling window managers. I am going to compare it to the usual stacking window manager I came from.</html:p>
        <html:p>I find that I usually lay out my windows in one of two ways: full-screen or side-by-side. Most desktops these days let you snap a window to one side of the screen, so you can view two windows at once. Rarely do I let a window float freely (even though Gnome's <html:em>always on top</html:em> setting can make that work nicely). So stacking gives me much more freedom than I'm using. And that freedom has a cost! My windows exist <html:em>somewhere</html:em> behind my current ones, and I have to either reach for the mouse or use Alt-Tab to get to them. I don't like using Alt-Tab because I struggle to remember the order of the stack of windows, so I end up having to press it an unknown number of times. It violates my principle that the computer should react to me, not me to it.</html:p>
        <html:p>Enter PaperWM. Windows snap to the side of the screen and are laid out predictably. Opening a new window puts it to the right of the current window. My screen does not fit all my windows, but my mind now does. I know that there's a terminal emulator to the left, a Firefox window to the right, and a Files app further right. I switch windows without thinking, because I know where my window are and how to get to them. I know up front how to get the computer into the state I want. I don't have to pause and <html:em>react</html:em>.</html:p>
        <html:p>My keybindings are centered around the Super key, which I only ever tap to launch apps, so using it as a modifier works well. Aside: I struggle to get started with <fr:link href="https://github.com/mogenson/PaperWM.spoon" type="external">PaperWM.spoon</fr:link> on my work machine, as macOS does not seem to have a similarly under-used key. I hold down Super and use the <html:code>left</html:code> and <html:code>right</html:code> arrow keys to move around the tape. <html:code>n</html:code> gives me a new window of the current application and <html:code>backspace</html:code> closes one. <html:code>t</html:code> picks up a window for rearranging the order. Two commands I find very useful are <html:code>f</html:code> and <html:code>r</html:code>. The first one maximizes a window and the second one cycles through three useful widths for side-by-side viewing. The <html:code>c</html:code> command centers the current window.</html:p>
        <html:p> I am by no means a power user and do not use much more than the above. You can also arrange windows in columns by putting them <html:code>i</html:code>n columns and pulling them back <html:code>o</html:code>ut, but I rarely do so. Perhaps if I used a screen larger than 13 inches, I would feel the need. No, what I get from PaperWM is predictability. It reduces the <html:em>friction</html:em> of using my computer. It simplifies window management enough that I can do it without thinking, without pausing, without losing my train of thought. It stays out of the way. That's how I enjoy using my computer.</html:p>
      </fr:mainmatter>
    </fr:tree>
    <fr:tree show-metadata="false">
      <fr:frontmatter>
        <fr:authors>
          <fr:author>
            <fr:link href="/forest/ahfrom/" title="Asta Halkjær From" uri="https://astahfrom.github.io/forest/ahfrom/" display-uri="ahfrom" type="local">Asta Halkjær From</fr:link>
          </fr:author>
        </fr:authors>
        <fr:date>
          <fr:year>2025</fr:year>
          <fr:month>8</fr:month>
          <fr:day>3</fr:day>
        </fr:date>
        <fr:uri>https://astahfrom.github.io/forest/miniflux/</fr:uri>
        <fr:display-uri>miniflux</fr:display-uri>
        <fr:route>/forest/miniflux/</fr:route>
        <fr:title text="Miniflux">Miniflux</fr:title>
        <fr:taxon>Software</fr:taxon>
      </fr:frontmatter>
      <fr:mainmatter>
        <html:figure><html:img src="/forest/bafkrmic3nvpgtacy6wpsm4q3v73le2lcsf3migrqcbgb3772oojtsra4my.png" alt="A list interface with buttons to &quot;mark as read&quot;, &quot;star&quot;, access &quot;external link&quot;, see &quot;comments&quot;, and similar." />
  <html:figcaption>Miniflux in a desktop browser showing a couple of old Lobsters articles.</html:figcaption></html:figure>
        <html:p><fr:link href="https://miniflux.app/" type="external">Miniflux</fr:link> is a feed reader and I have become a huge fan of feed readers. I don't really use the reader part, I always click through to the actual website, but I love having all my articles in one place. I could probably use another feed reader, but Miniflux runs in a Docker container on my home server and I can access it from anywhere on any device. I mostly use the Progressive Web App (PWA) on my phone and that has been working great.</html:p>
        <html:p>I follow different feeds, notably a <fr:link href="https://lobste.rs/tags" type="external">tag-based Lobsters feed</fr:link>, Danish news, and things like the <fr:link href="https://www.forester-notes.org/30FM/index.xml" type="external">Forester blog</fr:link>. I appreciate how new stuff automatically appears on the list. I don't have to keep track of what I've already read or become overwhelmed by busy news sites. I automatically stay up-to-date as it's all there in my feed. I read some articles quickly and others gets to sit there for a while until I find the time. It works  I really enjoy <html:em>consuming content</html:em> like this. At my leisure. Through a simple interface. On my terms.</html:p>
      </fr:mainmatter>
    </fr:tree>
    <fr:tree show-metadata="false">
      <fr:frontmatter>
        <fr:authors>
          <fr:author>
            <fr:link href="/forest/ahfrom/" title="Asta Halkjær From" uri="https://astahfrom.github.io/forest/ahfrom/" display-uri="ahfrom" type="local">Asta Halkjær From</fr:link>
          </fr:author>
        </fr:authors>
        <fr:date>
          <fr:year>2025</fr:year>
          <fr:month>8</fr:month>
          <fr:day>6</fr:day>
        </fr:date>
        <fr:uri>https://astahfrom.github.io/forest/ublock/</fr:uri>
        <fr:display-uri>ublock</fr:display-uri>
        <fr:route>/forest/ublock/</fr:route>
        <fr:title text="uBlock Origin">uBlock Origin</fr:title>
        <fr:taxon>Software</fr:taxon>
      </fr:frontmatter>
      <fr:mainmatter>
        <html:figure><html:img src="/forest/bafkrmidhw23yxyfnfw5hsi6mj5oebjgnvh5qap7dzjfjk5swu7bkbis7rm.png" alt="A control panel showing 2 domains, genius.com and images.genius.com, as allowed and 9 domains as blocked: adsafeprotected.com, ajax.googleapis.com, browser-intake-datadoghq.com, cookiepro.com, d3l739e8r8y9v7.cloudfront.net, doubleclick.net, googletagmanager.com, medialab.map.fastly.net, quantserve.com, scorecardresearch.com." />
  <html:figcaption>The uBlock Origin control panel for the Genius lyrics site.</html:figcaption></html:figure>
        <html:p><fr:link href="https://ublockorigin.com/" type="external">uBlock Origin</fr:link> is a browser extension for blocking content. It's famously an ad blocker, but I have found it very useful as a straight-up JavaScript blocker. I do most of my browsing on my phone and even though I am carrying around a supercomputer, it struggles with the modern web. Sites feel sluggish and unresponsive and they seem to make my phone kick other stuff out of its working memory. uBlock Origin to the rescue: most of the sites I visit work fine without JavaScript (and without custom fonts). The content is all there, it's just plastered in <html:em>extra functionality</html:em>.</html:p>
        <html:p>Here are some unscientific numbers to back up my scientific feelings. They are all taken from the Firefox Developer Tools of my <html:em>desktop</html:em> browser. I blocked only JavaScript for these numbers, not remote fonts.</html:p>
        <html:table style="text-align: right">
  <html:thead>
    <html:tr>
      <html:th>Page</html:th>
      <html:th>Requests</html:th>
      <html:th>Size (kB)</html:th>
      <html:th>Transferred (kB)</html:th>
      <html:th>Memory (MB)</html:th>
    </html:tr>
  </html:thead>

  <html:tbody>
    <html:tr>
      <html:th>Fandom (+)</html:th>
      <html:td>28</html:td>
      <html:td>1.700,63</html:td>
      <html:td>3.302,76</html:td>
      <html:td>37</html:td>
    </html:tr>
    <html:tr>
      <html:th>Fandom (-)</html:th>
      <html:td>16</html:td>
      <html:td>987,69</html:td>
      <html:td>362,13</html:td>
      <html:td>20</html:td>
    </html:tr>

    <html:tr />

    <html:tr>
      <html:th>Genius (+)</html:th>
      <html:td>30</html:td>
      <html:td>4.246,12</html:td>
      <html:td>3.024,50</html:td>
      <html:td>38</html:td>
    </html:tr>
    <html:tr>
      <html:th>Genius (-)</html:th>
      <html:td>14</html:td>
      <html:td>913,80</html:td>
      <html:td>370,08</html:td>
      <html:td>6</html:td>
    </html:tr>

    <html:tr />

    <html:tr>
      <html:th>DR (+)</html:th>
      <html:td>22</html:td>
      <html:td>2.429,63</html:td>
      <html:td>645,09</html:td>
      <html:td>33</html:td>
    </html:tr>
    <html:tr>
      <html:th>DR (-)</html:th>
      <html:td>9</html:td>
      <html:td>1.310,38</html:td>
      <html:td>299,76</html:td>
      <html:td>16</html:td>
    </html:tr>
  </html:tbody>
</html:table>
        <html:p>I think some of the space savings are from images that are not being loaded because the JavaScript does it. In any case, there are savings! Maybe such savings shouldn't matter on a supercomputer with a fast internet connection, but regardless of the numbers, uBlock Origin makes my browsing experience <html:em>feel</html:em> better. Oh, and blocking JavaScript makes most of those annoying cookie banners go away too. Good riddance.</html:p>
      </fr:mainmatter>
    </fr:tree>
    <fr:tree show-metadata="false">
      <fr:frontmatter>
        <fr:authors>
          <fr:author>
            <fr:link href="/forest/ahfrom/" title="Asta Halkjær From" uri="https://astahfrom.github.io/forest/ahfrom/" display-uri="ahfrom" type="local">Asta Halkjær From</fr:link>
          </fr:author>
        </fr:authors>
        <fr:date>
          <fr:year>2025</fr:year>
          <fr:month>8</fr:month>
          <fr:day>3</fr:day>
        </fr:date>
        <fr:uri>https://astahfrom.github.io/forest/pihole/</fr:uri>
        <fr:display-uri>pihole</fr:display-uri>
        <fr:route>/forest/pihole/</fr:route>
        <fr:title text="Pi-hole">Pi-hole</fr:title>
        <fr:taxon>Software</fr:taxon>
      </fr:frontmatter>
      <fr:mainmatter>
        <html:figure><html:img src="/forest/bafkrmid4wmapc6f66wklqgtwti7j36zvuska7d6o6q3xaucxu3wkxbjoky.png" alt="A bar graph with entries from 20:00 to 19:00. Each bar has three groups: blocked, resolved, and cached. There is a peak in traffic just before midnight and then again from 10:00 to 19:00." />
  <html:figcaption>A graph of queries blocked, cached and resolved by my Pi-hole.</html:figcaption></html:figure>
        <html:p><fr:link href="https://pi-hole.net/" type="external">Pi-hole</fr:link> is a DNS sinkhole. It makes me feel just a little bit more in control of my home network. Pi-hole functions as a local DNS server with customizable filters for which domains should actually be resolved and which should be blocked. I run it in Docker on my home server. The latest container images are built on Alpine Linux and are delightfully small. I have not set it up as the default DNS server for my entire home network, but most of our devices use it. I only use the <fr:link href="https://github.com/StevenBlack/hosts" type="external">default blocklist</fr:link>. Still, over the past week it has blocked 1 in 5 of the queries in my home. Sometimes the number is closer to 1 in 2.</html:p>
        <html:p>The vast majority of blocked queries right now are for <html:code>logs.netflix.com</html:code>. I have a so-called smart TV with a Netflix app that phones home every three seconds. Except, of course, that my Pi-hole gives it a phony number to call. I enjoy that. It similarly blocks the TV's own gossiping and various telemetry and analytics queries originating from other devices. I like that the Pi-hole gives me the power to thwart such chatter.</html:p>
        <html:p>More practically, my Pi-hole has a bunch of local DNS records that point my domains directly at the home server, so I bypass the internet round-trip when I'm on the same network.</html:p>
      </fr:mainmatter>
    </fr:tree>
  </fr:mainmatter>
  <fr:backmatter>
    <fr:tree show-metadata="false" hidden-when-empty="true">
      <fr:frontmatter>
        <fr:authors />
        <fr:title text="References">References</fr:title>
      </fr:frontmatter>
      <fr:mainmatter />
    </fr:tree>
    <fr:tree show-metadata="false" hidden-when-empty="true">
      <fr:frontmatter>
        <fr:authors />
        <fr:title text="Context">Context</fr:title>
      </fr:frontmatter>
      <fr:mainmatter />
    </fr:tree>
    <fr:tree show-metadata="false" hidden-when-empty="true">
      <fr:frontmatter>
        <fr:authors />
        <fr:title text="Backlinks">Backlinks</fr:title>
      </fr:frontmatter>
      <fr:mainmatter />
    </fr:tree>
    <fr:tree show-metadata="false" hidden-when-empty="true">
      <fr:frontmatter>
        <fr:authors />
        <fr:title text="Related">Related</fr:title>
      </fr:frontmatter>
      <fr:mainmatter />
    </fr:tree>
    <fr:tree show-metadata="false" hidden-when-empty="true">
      <fr:frontmatter>
        <fr:authors />
        <fr:title text="Contributions">Contributions</fr:title>
      </fr:frontmatter>
      <fr:mainmatter />
    </fr:tree>
  </fr:backmatter>
</fr:tree>
